Alright, today's דף ט"ז Daf Tet Zayin and we picked up actually
a little bit ahead in the middle of ט"ז Tet Zayin and
we
are
we are about three lines before.
Thank you.
We are two lines before the lines get wide. הכי נמי מסתברא.
Hachi Nami Mistabra. So we're way into ט"ז. Tet Zayin. So basically
for the people that weren't here yesterday and just to catch you
up, the issue is the following: that
because our משנה Mishnah speaks about what the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
would do on a daily basis to prepare for the seven days
leading up to יום כיפור Yom Kippur and it said that he
would do
the קטורת Ketoret and light the נרות. Nerot. And the problem is
that that order is the reverse of what we find elsewhere. Elsewhere
it says he would light the נרות Nerot or the normal order
of the day would be the נרות Nerot and then the קטורת.
Ketoret. So the answer the גמרא Gemara pretty much settled on is
that there was a that the נרות Nerot were broken up. There
was five cleaning of the נרות, Nerot, then there was not the
lighting, cleaning in the morning, then the burning of the קטורת, Ketoret,
then two. So some of the משניות Mishnayot that say קטורת Ketoret
and נרות Nerot were talking about the five and then the קטורת,
Ketoret, and then it said the קטורת Ketoret and נרות Nerot were
talking about the קטורת Ketoret and the two because it was five
קטורת Ketoret two. That was the basic answer. But along the way,
one of the answers had been that the contradiction was between משניות
Mishnayot in יומא Yoma and משניות Mishnayot in תמיד Tamid and that
the author of תמיד Tamid was a different author than the author
of the משניות Mishnayot in יומא, Yoma, which is not a big
deal, very often the גמרא Gemara says okay fine, it's a debate
of the משניות. Mishnayot. But what was interesting about the answer was
it described an author to the entire מסכת תמיד, Masechet Tamid, to
all of the משניות Mishnayot of תמיד, Tamid, and it did it
based on a reference of a particular תנא, Tanna, actually more obscure
תנא, Tanna, רבי שמעון בן משלמא, Rabbi Shimon ben Meshulma,
based on a reference that there was of him in a ברייתא.
Braita. So based on that structure, like a contradiction particularly around issues
of the עבודה Avodah in בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and then an
answer that ascribes all of the משניות Mishnayot of one מסכת Masechet
to a particular individual, we've been introduced to the סוגיא Sugya right
now, which is again, only by this form is it related to
us. It's not about יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it's not about the
daily עבודה, Avodah, and that was a contradiction that in a משנה
Mishnah in מדות, Middot, it mentioned in תמיד Tamid it mentioned that
the room where they would have the שחיטה Shechita for the קרבנות
Korbanot would be in one location in this בית המוקד, Beit HaMoked,
in this large room where they had a fire for priests to
warm themselves up. And in another משנה Mishnah in תמיד Tamid it
mentioned that that room was a different chamber. So how do you
deal with this contradiction? And the גמרא's Gemara answer was that the
משניות Mishnayot in תמיד Tamid is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov, again, a particular תנא Tanna is the author of all
of the משניות Mishnayot in מסכת תמיד Masechet Tamid and מדות, Middot,
of all the משניות Mishnayot in מדות. Middot. And it did it
because there was another משנה Mishnah in מדות Middot where רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov is describing how different rooms were
used and רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov said, "Oh,
I forgot what that room was used for." So the question is,
why are you quoting somebody who just says he doesn't know? And
the fact that he was saying, "here's this room, this room, this
room, this room I forgot how it was used for," sounds like
he was the סתם, Stam, he's the anonymous voice of those משניות
Mishnayot in תמיד. Tamid. So that's somehow the structure that we're dealing
with is to try to deal with this contradiction of where was
this particular room for the
קרבנות, Korbanot, a contradiction between תמיד Tamid and מדות, Middot, we say
the author of all of מדות Middot was this רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. Okay, and we do it based on
the fact that in another place in מדות Middot he says, "I
forgot what that thing was used for." And now we're going to
continue with another answer to that. So let's take a look.
הכי נמי מסתברא. Hachi Nami Mistabra. That also makes sense for רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. He did not. כל הכתלים
שהיו שם. Kol haktalim she'hayu sham. דתנן, Detnan, now again we're quoting
a משנה Mishnah in מדות Middot and we're going to try, as
you'll see, try to demonstrate that the author of this סתם משנה
Stam Mishnah in מדות Middot is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov. כל הכתלים שהיו שם, Kol haktalim she'hayu sham, all the
walls that were there in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, היו גבוהים,
hayu gevohim, they were very very high. Right? The gates were twenty
אמה amah high and the walls were even higher. Okay? חוץ מכותל
מזרחי, chutz mikotel mizrachi, except for the easternmost
gate, כשהכהן שורף את הפרה, keshehakohen soref et haparah, that the כהן
Kohen who burns with the פרה parah would stand at the הר
המשחה Har HaMishchah and
ומכוון ורואה כנגד פתחו של היכל umekaven vero'eh keneged pitcho shel heichal
and would see into the opening of the היכל Heichal בשעת הזיית
הדם bisheat hazzayat hadam at the time of the sprinkling of the
blood. So what does this mean?
It means that there you have your... okay, we all remember from
תמיד. Tamid. What?
We all remember it from תמיד. Tamid.
I don't even have to discuss this,
you guys can see this. Okay, here is your... here is your...
okay here you see here's your הר המשחה. Har HaMishchah. Here's your
Mount of Olives and here's your הר הבית. Har HaBayit. No, these
aren't city walls. These are... these aren't city walls. These are not
the city walls, these are the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash walls. Okay.
Here's your הר הבית. Har Habayit. Now the כהן, Kohein, the כהן
Kohein who did the פרה, Parah, again we're back to the פרה,
Parah, would stand here and he'd have to. Why are these markers
already dead? And he'd have his פרה Parah just slaughtered. The תורה
Torah says והזה אל נוכח פני אהל מועד, Vehiza el nochach pnei
Ohel Moed,
פני אהל מועד. pnei Ohel Moed. So he has to be looking
sort of opposite the opening of אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, which is
here on הר הבית. Har Habayit. Here's the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
right? And he has to be opposite it. So he has to
be facing it. This is the entrance, this is the east. Right?
That's the east, north, west. Okay. So the only thing is that
חז"ל Chazal understand that means that when he's looking at it, it's
not just he's facing the general direction, he has to be directly
being able to see the opening of אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. Now
the opening of אהל מועד Ohel Moed is not the
whole מקדש, Mikdash, right? Here's the עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. I can't
believe these markers are already junk. Okay.
Here's the עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. Okay, right? And then here is
the this is the normal עזרה Azarah with the מזבח, Mizbeiach, right?
And then this is the היכל, Heichal, right? And this is the
קדש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim etc. Okay. And the פני אהל מועד pnei
Ohel Moed is the door to the היכל, Heichal, right? Because that's
the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, that represents the אהל מועד Ohel Moed
of the תורה. Torah. Is that clear, right? This is open air,
this is whatever. So he has to be able to stand here
and see actually that door. Problem is that all these things have
walls, right? There's walls here before the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim and
a door here and a door here. Now luckily all of those
doors are directly parallel one another. So if everything were level and
he himself was standing, and we're going to assume he's standing here,
then he could see straight through. Okay? That's the idea. The only
problem being
that they're not level, that this is all built on a mountain.
So they would level off a space for some of the ground
and then there'd be a rise and then they'd level and then
there'd be a rise. So the way this actually is going to
look, I'll draw it down here and this'll be like a side
view, okay, is that this would be עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim and
then there'd be some steps
and then you'd have, right,
עזרת ישראל Ezras Yisrael and then there'd be some steps and then
you'd have the היכל, Heichal, right?
שער ניקנור Shaar Nikanor goes through one of them?
Right. Right, you have these steps, okay, going from so you flatten
a space and then you go arise and then you flatten and
arise. So what he's going to have to be able to do
is see, now we're assuming he's not looking in an upward angle,
we're assuming he's looking in a straight angle. So we're going to
have to be able to assume that standing here he can look
through this and then even after all those
steps, ah, it's getting drawn to scale. Okay, but anyway, even after
all of those steps, the very tip of this will at least
be in line with the very bottom
of that and that you'll be able to at least see a
piece of that opening. Okay? So that's the challenge.
Now do we know I guess הר הבית Har Habayit is certainly
much taller than הר המשחה, Har Hamishcha, right?
Well, we yes, so you couldn't just say stand higher and see
through low. Right. So we're assuming no, that he's like standing as
level as possible and seeing through all the gates.
He's tall. Always.
What? You need to all the doorways are twenty אמה. Ammah. Correct.
And that's what we're going to be discussing. Now the thing is,
let's take a look at again what it says. It says דתנן
כל הכתלים שהיו שם היו גבוהים חוץ מכותל מזרחי שהכהן השורף את
הפרה עומד בהר המשחה ומכוון ורואה כנגד פתחו של היכל בשעת הזאת
הדם. Detnan kol hakotlim shehayu sham hayu gevohim chutz mikotel mizrachi shehakohein
hasoreif es haparah omeid behar hamishcha umechavein vero'eh keneged pitcho shel heichal
bisha'as haza'as hadam. So
it
says the easternmost wall here,
right, outside of
עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, this wall had to be low so that
he could start by seeing through the gate here of עזרת נשים.
Ezras Nashim. Because if this wall was high, and there's also going
to be a rise from the outer wall, the retaining wall, right,
that's sort of even around the עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. If you
have could see those pictures I should have brought one of them
but there's yeah okay that's the כותל, Kosel, right that's the side
well, if it's the כותל Kosel actually רש"י Rashi makes it sound
like it's the כותל Kosel of the actual הר הבית Har Habayit
although it's not so clear to me that's what we're talking about
but you know before you get to the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim
there's a wall around, there's the סורג Soreg and the חיל Chayil
and there's this space even before the עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. So
that's the wall we're talking about here. So he also had to
get through that door and then he started he'd have to start
even lower, right, as it were and if he's straight it would
never work. So this wall is low so that the doors he
doesn't have to worry about seeing through this door. This is lower,
he can start by being at a higher position and start by
seeing through the door of עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. That's the idea.
So let's take a look at how that works.
Okay,
so let's take a look. So, all right.
Now, so now we're going to see according to whom did that
outer wall have to be low and could you not manage it?
Okay, ותנן V'tenan, *U-tnan*: כל הפתחים *Kol HaP'tachim*, so all the doorways,
שהיו שם *SheHayu Sham*, גבוהים עשרים אמה Amah *Gvohim Esrim Ama*, were
20 amot tall and ורחבן עשר אמות Amos. *V'rochban Eser Amot*, 10
amot wide, which isn't relevant for us yet. ותנן V'tenan, *U-tnan*, and
another משנה Mishna *Mishnah* there, all these are משניות Mishnayos, *Mishnayot* in
מדות Middos *Midot*, teaches: לפנים ממנו סורג *Lifnim Mimenu Soreg*. Inside the
wall, the outer wall that precedes the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim *Ezrat
Nashim*, was a space called סורג *Soreg*, and like was some type
of a latticework. ותנן *U-tnan*, לפנים ממנו *Lifnim Mimenu*, from the סורג
*Soreg*, החיל *HaChel*, was open space. This was before the עזרת נשים
Ezrat Nashim. *Ezrat Nashim*, עשר אמות Amos. *Eser Amot*, 10 amot open
space. Again, distance isn't going to interest us as height. And this
is where it becomes interesting. ושתים עשרה מעלות היו שם *U'shtayim Esreh
Ma'alot Hayu Sham*. There were 12 steps getting from the סורג *Soreg*,
this open space before the עזרת נשים *Ezrat Nashim*, to the door
of the עזרת נשים *Ezrat Nashim*. To the top, okay. היו שם
רום מעלה חצי אמה Amah ושלחה חצי אמה Amah. *Hayu Sham Rom
Ma'alah Chatzi Ama V'shilchah Chatzi Ama*. Half אמה Amah *Ama* high and
half אמה Amah, *Ama* would go in. So it would be like
the 12 steps
would rise
six אמות Amos, *Amot*, each one would be half אמה Amah *Ama*
over distance of six אמות Amos, *Amot*. Okay, so that's from the
סורג *Soreg* to the עזרת נשים *Ezrat Nashim*.
Look at it, I really can't believe I don't have one decent
marker here.
Okay. Anyway, so if we look at it, draw the same thing
here, right, so basically,
okay, so here you have your סורג *Soreg*, you have your open
space, and then you have your steps,
okay, and your steps go up, 12 steps times a half, so
your steps go up six אמות Amos, *Amot*. Okay, so now we're
six אמות Amos, *Amot* off of where the סורג *Soreg* is, and
then this begins the עזרת נשים *Ezrat Nashim*.
Okay? So we've gone up six אמות Amos *Amot*. All right. Okay.
ותנן *U-tnan*, okay, ושתים עשרה מעלות היו שם רום מעלה חצי אמה
Amah ושלחה חצי אמה Amah *U'shtayim Esreh Ma'alot Hayu Sham Rom Ma'alah
Chatzi Ama V'shilchah Chatzi Ama*. וחמש עשרה מעלות היו שם *V'chamesh Esreh
Ma'alot Hayu Sham*,
so from the עזרת נשים *Ezrat Nashim* to עזרת ישראל Ezras Yisrael,
*Ezrat Yisrael*, or עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael *Ezrat Yisrael* to עזרת נשים
*Ezrat Nashim*, same difference, there were 15 steps. רום מעלה חצי אמה
Amah *Rom Ma'alah Chatzi Ama*, it was a half, each step was
half אמה Amah. *Ama* tall, ושלחה חצי אמה Amah, *V'shilchah Chatzi Ama*,
and half אמה Amah *Ama* sort of wide, instep half אמה amah
*Ama*.
So from the עזרת נשים *Ezrat Nashim*, sorry, this is the חיל
*HaChel*, the סורג *Soreg* is the wall, okay, and great, and
here's the חיל *HaChel*, okay, so that goes up six אמות amot
*Amot*. Then we have 15 of these steps, okay, 15 times a
half gets you seven and a half from the עזרת נשים *Ezrat
Nashim* to the עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael *Ezrat Yisrael*.
This is רום מעלה *Rom Ma'alah* means it goes height.
רום מעלה *Rom Ma'alah*, the height of a step was חצי אמה
amah *Chatzi Ama* and its instep was חצי אמה amah, *Chatzi Ama*.
Okay, so we've gone now from the outer wall here, right, six
אמות amot. *Amot* high to get to the עזרת נשים *Ezrat Nashim*,
and seven and a half אמות amot. *Amot* to get to the
עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael *Ezrat Yisrael*.
25 feet?
13 and a half אמות amot *Amot*, yeah, a little less, 20
feet something like that. Yep. Okay. Okay. The 15 מעלות *Ma'alot* by
the way are like the 15 שיר המעלות *Shir HaMa'alot* and so
on. Okay.
Now, from עזרת נשים *Ezrat Nashim*, okay. ותנן בין האולם ולמזבח *U-tnan
Ben HaUlam V'laMizbe'ach*, the space between the אולם Ulam, *Ulam*, the אולם
Ulam. *Ulam* was the hallway before the היכל Heichel *Heichal*, also covered
and part of the same structure. Between that and the מזבח Mizbeiach
*Mizbe'ach* was כ"ב אמה amah, *Kaf-Bet Ama*, 22 amot. ושתים עשרה מעלות
היו שם *U'shtayim Esreh Ma'alot Hayu Sham*, and to get from that
space after the מזבח Mizbeiach, *Mizbe'ach* to get to the steps that
led up to the היכל Heichel *Heichal*, the אולם Ulam *Ulam* which
was like the antechamber of the היכל Heichel *Heichal*, were 12 steps.
רום מעלה חצי אמה amah ושלחה חצי אמה amah *Rom Ma'alah Chatzi
Ama V'shilchah Chatzi Ama*, again it's six- a half אמה amah *Ama*
each one. So here you're at the עזרת ישראל Yisrael *Ezrat Yisrael*,
then you've got the עזרת כהנים Ezras Kohanim, *Ezrat Kohanim*, then you
have the מזבח Mizbeiach *Mizbe'ach*, okay, this is the מזבח Mizbeiach *Mizbe'ach*
with the ramp, okay, and then you've got these steps leading up
to now here is the אולם Ulam *Ulam* and the היכל Heichel
*Heichal*. And those steps, okay, to get you up now, so you're
walking from the open-air space of the מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbe'ach*. So if
you're standing here and you're walking up to get into the היכל,
Heichal. right, which is where the שולחן Shulchan and the מנורה Menorah
were, that's another twelve steps, which is another six אמות. amot So
if you're standing here, the height from the outer wall till the
till the היכל Heichal, is six, seven and a half, and six
is twelve and thirteen, nineteen and a half. Nineteen and a half.
Now the doors are twenty אמות. amos, So in theory, if you
were looking at the very tip of this door, right, if this
is twenty אמות, amos. right, twenty אמות, amos, and you looked at
the very tip here, you'd be able to get to the very
bottom half אמה ama there because this is a nineteen and a
half אמה rise, twenty אמות, amot so if you were looking straight
in here, you could see the very bottom of the doorway there.
So you don't know why you have to have a low wall,
right, this outer wall here, because you could still manage it by
going straight there. Just barely, you could look at the bottom half
אמה. Okay, so let's take a look.
Okay, ותנן, we just did that. ותנן, so so we don't know
why you needed to have a low wall, but we have another
משנה Mishnah: that says רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov,
remember he's the one we're trying to argue is the author of
these משניות, Mishnayot רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
Omer, מעלה
הייתה שם, Ma'alah haysa sham, if no no no, you're forgetting another
rise, there was a rise there in the in the space between
the before the what do you call it,
before you got to the אולם, Ulam
וגבוה אמה, V'gavoha amah, it was an אמה tall, ודוכן נתונה לה,
V'duchan nesuna lah, and there was a platform on it, ובו שלש
מעלות, U'vo shalosh ma'alos, and to get from first of all this
rise to the platform was another three steps, של חצי חצי אמה,
Shel chatzi chatzi amah, again each step was a half an אמה,
and that would be the דוכן Duchan where the לויים Levi'im would
stand. Okay, so now we've got now he basically says that this
thing, this thing would not start after these 60 after these twelve
steps. Before you got there there was like another rise and that
rise would be you'd have to go up an אמה or maybe
it's a question would everybody have to go up the אמה plus
the height of the דוכן Duchan or the דוכן Duchan was smaller,
but at least there'd be another אמה before you would get to
the door of the אולם. Ulam So according to him there'd be
no way to see through this to the door of the אולם
Ulam, because the door of the אולם Ulam would not be nineteen
and a half, it would be twenty and a half or higher,
there would be yet one more rise to go. So according to
him you understand why, right, why this wall had to be, so
if the wall here was high,
now he's going to explain too why the wall was low. If
the wall was high, right, then there's no way you can see
there, you can't see through the door, that'll get you too low,
you can't see over the wall, you could have a
high wall and a higher and an even higher,
right, of course, well or you could of course stand with the
height you have, but if all the gates were twenty and the
wall was high, right, there's no way you could see it. But
if however basically you've got the well let's see how that's going
to work. You're going to have to stand
well either way though, either way you're going to have to stand
higher than the gate. I mean if the wall ended with the
gate and you stood right here you could see it. Of course
once you're standing there, but the point is this wall could not
be too high because if the wall was too high you'd have
to stand way high and see it at a downward angle, and
there's an assumption that you're not looking at it at a downward
angle or upward angle, you're looking at it at a level angle.
Okay, so this thing here is still visible for like the next
אמה or half of an אמה. So you can't so you have
to be able to be standing right here and looking at it,
so this wall can't be really you know, the wall can't be
higher flush with the gate, it can't be higher than
on a higher gate too.
Yeah, because it said all the gates were twenty אמות, amot. so
you could have said the gate that gate was bigger. Instead he
says that wall was lower. Okay, fine.
Anyway, is the מזבח mizbe'ach, in front of the היכל Heichal or
is it someplace else?
No, the מזבח, mizbe'ach the outer מזבח mizbe'ach
is why I drew it, the outer מזבח mizbe'ach is here, and
then you have to go up, that's in the open courtyard, and
then you have to go up and you get to the היכל
Heichal, here.
Right,
עזרת
כהנים, Kohanim עזרת ישראל, the
outer
right.
All right, so let's take a look.
Okay, so you see it's another proof that it's רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. אי אמרת בשלמא רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
היא, Ee amrat bishlama Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov hi, if the סתם
Stam author of מדות Middot is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov, היינו דאיכסי ליה פתחא, Hainu d'ichasi lei pischa, we understand
why the you know we understand why the opening at the outer
wall is covered, does not does not give you a sightline to
the, or say it the other way, excuse me, the פתחא, Pischa,
the opening of the of the אולם Ulam and the היכל Heichal
is covered because your sightline is covered because it's too high. אלא
אי אמרת רבנן, Ela ee amrat Rabbanan, if it's רבנן, Rabbanan, הא
איכא פלגא דאמתא דמתחזי ליה פתחא, Ha ika palga d'amsa d'mis'chazei lei
pischa, that there's a last half אמה, the bottom half אמה of
the opening of the אולם Ulam, is visible, because it only went
up nineteen and a half אמות amot and it would be visible
by the. outer through the top of the outer door. בגויה, Begaveih,
in it. אלא לאו שמע מינה רבי אליעזר בן יעקב היא, Ella
lav shema mina Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov hi, so you see that
the author of מידות Middot is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov. So we have two evidence. One is that in one
place רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov just says oh
I forgot, and the fact that he's bothered to say he forgot
is not interesting unless he was the author of the משניות himself
and saying he forgot. And the other is this idea that you
have to have this wall low so you can see the opening,
and according to the—before you got to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov, you didn't—you could actually see through the tip of
this door to the bottom door of the—of the—of the אולם, Ulam
and the only way you couldn't is if you assumed the אולם
Ulam, was a little bit higher, which is what רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says, it's an אמה higher, and then
it's no longer visible through the door. So again we have a
proof that it's done according to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov. רב אדא
בר אהבא אמר, Rav Adda bar Ahava amar, רב אדא בר אהבא
Rav Adda bar Ahava says, הא מני רבי יהודה היא. ha mani
Rabbi Yehuda hi. No, no, no. The author of מידות Middot is
actually—there's two ways of reading this line, I'll read it this way
first. The author of מידות Middot is not רבי אליעזר בן יעקב,
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, the author of מידות Middot is רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. And it's—according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, you needed to
have a low wall and you couldn't see straight. Why according to
him did you need a low wall and you couldn't see straight?
Not because of this extra אמה for the place for the דוכן
duchan for the לוים. Levi'im. No, no, no. There's another reason that
your sight line was blocked. What is it? דתניא, Detanya, רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, המזבח ממוצע ועומד באמצע עזרה, Hamizbe'ach memutza ve-omed
be-emtza Azara, ושלושים ושתיים אמות היו לו. ve-shloshim u-shtayim amot hayu lo.
The מזבח mizbe'ach was exactly midpoint in the עזרה, Azara, and it
was thirty-two אמות amot wide. עשר אמות כנגד פתחו של היכל, esser
amot keneged pitcho shel Heichal, אחת עשרה אמה מצפון, achat esrei amah
mitzafon, ואחת עשרה אמה מדרום, ve-achat esrei amah midarom, נמצא מזבח מכוון
כנגד היכל וכותליו. nimtza mizbe'ach mechuvon keneged Heichal ve-kotlav.
So what he said is the following, let's draw another picture here.
He says that you've
got—okay,
you've got the—the—sort of dimension here of the whole עזרה, Azara, right?
The עזרת נשים was 135 by 135. Okay, the rest of the
עזרה Azara was 135 by I think it's 187 or close, no
177. The עזרת ישראל is a subset of? No, no, this is
עזרת נשים. Right.
עזרת ישראל is small, right? Right, yeah.
This is sort of like this—is considered בגדול begadol the עזרה Azara
proper, this עזרת ישראל and then עזרת כוהנים, Ezrat Kohanim, and then
here's the מזבח, mizbe'ach.
and then this is
אולם Ulam,
and the היכל. Heichal. And all of—and this is all covered. Okay?
So he says this מזבח mizbeach is thirty-two אמות. amot And it
was midpoint, and the כבש—I kevesh should also mention, we'll get to
later, is thirty-two אמות. amot It was midpoint across the length here
of the עזרה Azara which was—which was 135, the width of the
עזרה Azara was 135. Okay, so if it was midpoint here, basically,
okay, so midpoint is about sixty-seven and a half. Okay, so anyway
it's right over here. Okay, we'll worry about exact dimensions in a
minute. Now, if it was thirty-two אמות wide, okay, this doorway, by
the way, is—is ten. The doorway to the אולם, the door to
the היכל, Heichal we remember said all the doorways were ten wide.
Okay? So the middle ten is opposite the doorway, okay, and then
you've got—if it's thirty-two, you've got eleven here and eleven here. Okay,
that's exactly where it was located. Okay, that's what it says. מכוון
כנגד פתחו של היכל, Mechuvon keneged pitcho shel Heichal, אחת עשרה אמה
מצפון, achat esrei amah mitzafon, אחת עשרה אמה מדרום, achat esrei amah
midarom, נמצא מזבח מכוון כנגד היכל וכותליו. nimtza mizbe'ach mechuvon keneged Heichal
ve-kotlav.
Now why is it equal to the היכל Heichal. and the כותלים?
kotlim? Because the wall here of the היכל, Heichal. this is actually—ten
is this doorway, היכל Hechal. was
twenty wide, okay? So you have ten here, you have five on
each side, and the walls were actually six. Okay, so this, you
know, the walls of the היכל. Hechal,
Okay, so the מזבח mizbeach here was exactly opposite, I'm sorry it's
so sloppy but I hope you can see. Okay, the middle ten
were exactly opposite the door, you have eleven here, eleven is equal
to the space of the היכל plus the six of the wall,
the space and the six thickness of the wall. So the מזבח
mizbeach was exactly in line with the היכל. That's what he's saying,
okay? Dead center and exactly in line with the היכל. Now how
is that relevant to us? The reason it's relevant to us is
that the מזבח mizbeach was nine אמות tall.
You got the height of the מזבח.
mizbeach So if you have to be out here and you have
to be on הר הזיתים Har HaZeitim and looking in, according to
him, you got your vision blocked, right? Doesn't matter, you know, one
extra אמה, not one extra אמה, this here, boom, you know, you
got—you hit a nine אמה tall thing, okay? You're—you're blocked. So remember
the rise here, right, was only six אמות, whereas the steps going
up to the אולם six אמות. But this is nine אמות, so
you now have lost, you know, you now if you just barely
made it with the six אמה rise, but now you've got this
big obstruction nine אמה tall, there's no way you're going to see
over it unless, again, you're at the, you know, there's a low
wall and you can see over the low wall. So he says
that's the explanation why you needed a low wall, not because of
the additional rise of the ground, but because the מזבח mizbeach was
dead center.
Okay, how's lowering the wall help you with the obstruction? Lowering the
wall would only help you with the obstruction if the fact is
that you could start higher back and see over the wall.
So according to that, you actually do have to, you know, or
just start higher and see straight. Right? So if you've got, again,
right, if this is you, right, if you have a very tall
wall, then the only way you're going to see is by looking
through here. But if the wall is low, right, and then you
start a little bit higher, you know, then you can start higher
and clear the obstruction. Right. And then the fact that there's a
big מזבח mizbeach here doesn't matter, if you've got a low wall,
you can see like this. But if the wall were super high,
apparently, that would just not make it possible. Right? You'd have to
be too high, or maybe even הר הזיתים Har Hazeisim wasn't high
enough. But if the wall here is low, then you could just
start a little bit higher and see over the wall and over
the מזבח mizbeach and so on.
Yes, it's very thorough. The tower is the, you see the, they
open all the gates.
Yeah, they open all the gates and he has to see the
doorway of the היכל. The doorway, right, the door. He doesn't have
to see actually into the היכל, presumably not. Right. Okay, so now
the גמרא's Gemara going to challenge this. גמרא Gemara says one minute,
אי סלקא דעתך I salka daitach מדות כרבי יהודה היא. Middot k'Rebbi
Yehuda hi. You're trying to say that מדות Middot, is רבי יהודה,
Rebbi Yehuda, right?
And that's why you needed a low wall because the מזבח mizbeach
was in the way.
מזבח באמצע עזרה מי משכחת לה? Mizbeach b'emtza azara mi mishkachat lah?
Offhand, that can't be! From other evidence in מדות, Middot I'll show
you that the מזבח mizbeach, was not in the smack middle. So
you're trying to say the author of מדות is רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda and that's why you needed a low wall, but there's other
evidence in מסכת מדות Masechet Middot that the מזבח mizbeach was not
רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda position, was not smack in the middle. והתנן,
V'hatnan, we taught in
the
משנה: כל העזרה הייתה אורך מאה ושמונים ושבע על רוחב מאה ושלושים
וחמש. Kol ha'azara hayta orech me'ah u'shemonim v'sheva al rochav me'ah u'sheloshim
v'chamesh. 187 by 135. ממזרח למערב מאה ושמונים ושבע. Mimizrach lema'arav me'ah
u'shemonim v'sheva. From the east to the west 187.
מקום דריסת רגלי ישראל י"א אמה.
Makom drisat raglei Yisrael
yud alef amah. מקום דריסת רגלי כהנים י"א אמה. Makom drisat raglei
Kohanim yud alef amah. Now we're going to do the math.
Okay, so you have where the ישראל could go, that was 11.
Sorry for being so slow.
You have where the כהנים could go, that was another 11.
Okay, we're going to figure out how you get to 187.
מקום דריסת רגלי ישראל י"א, מקום דריסת רגלי כהנים י"א. Makom drisat
raglei Yisrael yud alef, makom drisat raglei Kohanim yud alef. מזבח שלושים
ושתיים. Mizbeach sheloshim u'shtayim. The altar here now was 32 by 32.
There was 32 in each direction, it was a square. That's 32.
שלושים ושתיים. Sheloshim u'shtayim. בין אולם למזבח עשרים ושתיים. Bein Ulam l'Mizbeach
esrim u'shtayim. The space here
between
the אולם, right, and the מזבח mizbeach was 22.
Okay, עשרים ושתיים. esrim u'shtayim. וההיכל
מאה אמה. V'haHechal me'ah amah.
וההיכל V'haHechal with the אולם, this entire structure with the antechamber was
100. So let's do the math: 22 steps, right, the 22? Yes,
the 22 is included in the steps. Okay, so that's 54, and
22 is 76, and 100 is 176, and now we're left with
11 behind.
Okay, that's behind.
י"א אמה אחרי בית הכפורת. Yud alef amah acharei beit hakapporet. Okay,
so that's how you get 187. Now we're going to figure out
the the other dimension. The other dimension is relevant to us because
we want to see where the מזבח mizbeach is. Okay, מן הדרום
לצפון מאה ושלושים וחמש. Min hadarom latzafon me'ah u'sheloshim v'chamesh. 135. הכבש
והמזבח שישים ושתיים. Hakevesh v'haMizbeach shishim u'shtayim.
So the ramp and the מזבח mizbeach was, right, this was 32
as we said by 32, the ramp is also 32, so this
thing combined here is 64. Okay? שישים ושתיים. Shishim u'shtayim. מן המזבח
ולטבעות ח' אמות. Min haMizbeach v'lataba'ot chet amot.
Now
they would have here בית המטבחיים. Beis hamitbachayim.
Right, they would have the place where they put the rings that
they put the necks of the animals in and they would be
at the north. Right, remember this is the north, this is the
east, because the קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim were slaughtered in the north,
so might as well have the whole slaughtering place set up in
the north. So these were the rings, the טבעות, taba'ot, where they'd
put the necks of the animals in. Okay, so this is 64.
Okay, 32 and 32. Where was it?
שישים ושתיים. Shishim u'shtayim. Oh, I'm sorry, because it was 32. 32
and the ramp was 30, I'm sorry, 62.
32 and 30, okay, 62. מן המזבח לטבעות ח' אמות, Min hamizbeach
latabaot chet amot, so eight אמות until you get to the rings.
מקום הטבעות עשרים וארבע, Makom hatabaot esrim vearba, so there's a lot
of space for the rings, okay? So there would be eight here,
the rings themselves would be twenty-four, and that would be a big
space for שחטינג shechting the animals, עשרים וארבע. esrim vearba.
מן הטבעות לשולחנות ארבע, Min hatabaot lashulchanot arba, then you'd have four
until you got to the tables. Okay, then here you'd have the
שולחנות, shulchanot, the tables you would use to rinse the innards of
the animal. Okay, so to the tables is four אמות. ארבע. Arba.
מן השולחנות—now Min hashulchanot it did not tell you how much space
was for the שולחנות, shulchanot, which is interesting. Okay, so one of
these large רש"י'ס Rashis is trying to figure some of this stuff
out. We're going to assume, although it doesn't tell us that, we're
going to assume that there was four אמות for the tables, okay.
Michael can argue with me about that later, but there's a big
רש"י Rashi about it. Okay, so that's four אמות for the שולחנות.
shulchanot. מן השולחנות לננסים ארבע, Min hashulchanot lananansim arba, from the שולחנות
shulchanot to the hooks were four. The hooks were where they would
hang up, you know, they would flay the animal, right? So those
would be the hooks that they put the animals on and flay
them.
Isn't a ננס nanas like a dwarf? Yeah, but it means like
these little posts with hooks, pillars with hooks.
Okay, ארבע. arba. מן הננסים לכותל Min hananasim lakotel doesn't tell you
how much space for the hooks. From the hooks to the wall,
עזרה ח' אמות Azara chet amot is eight. Okay, so we didn't
say the space of the hooks, but let's see how much we
have. 70, 62 and 8 is 70, and 28 is 98. Okay,
and another
8—I said 24 for
the—wait, didn't you
say it was 24?
No, 70 and then I added these two, 28. Oh, 28, okay.
28 is 98 and 8 is 106. Okay, and 8 is
114. Okay, plus the space of the rings, okay, but we're
basically—basically based on what we said of 135, we're 21 shy. Okay,
it says לכותל ח' אמות, lakotel chet amot, והמותר—okay, vehamotar did I
do that right? I think I did—והמותר בין הכבש לכותל ומקום הננסים,
vehamotar bein hakevesh lakotel umakom hananasim, and the rest you divide between
the space used for the ננסים nanasim and the space here between
the wall and the ramp. So if there's 21 left,
you divide it equally.
Well right, again, that's what the big רש"י Rashi is. רש"י Rashi
assumes for now we'll divide it equally, so there'll be ten and
a half here and ten and a half here. Okay, so anyway,
if you do that and you assume that it was divided equally,
okay, here's basically the part that matters for us now. Ignore all
of this, okay, but if you've got ten and a half אמות
here and 62 here to the end of the מזבח, mizbeach that
gets you 72 and a half. Okay, what's the midpoint of 135?
67 and a half. This gets you 72 and a half. Most
of the מזבח mizbeach is in the south. It is not midpoint,
right? The only way to get this midpoint is there to be
a huge gap between the wall and the beginning of this. All
right, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says, you see it is
not midpoint.
So it says, ואי סלקא דעתך ve'ei salka dach if you think
מידות רבי יהודה היא Midos Rabbi Yehuda hi that מידות Midos is
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, מזבח באמצע עזרה מי משכחת לה? mizbeach be'emtza
Azara mi meshkachat lah? The altar's not going to be in the
middle. הא רובו דמזבח בדרום קאי, ha rubo demizbeach bedarom kai, most
of it is in the south, because if there's again only 10,
72 and a half, only five אמות of the 32 אמה מזבח
is in the—actually, you know, in—over the line. אלא לאו שמע מינה
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב היא, שמע מינה. Ela lav shema mina Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov hi, shema mina. So you see, forget saying it's
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and that the reason you needed a low
wall was to get over the מזבח because the מזבח was smack
in the center. You see elsewhere in מידות Midos that the מזבח
is not in the south, the מזבח is off to the side,
and therefore the reason you needed a low wall was because it's
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov who spoke about there
being another rise, and the other rise required there to be a
low wall so you could see in, otherwise you couldn't, and that
fits with the idea that it's also רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov who says, "Oh, I forgot what they used this
room for." So again, that sounds like he is the סתם stam
voice of מסכת מידות. Masechet Midos. So we've now resolved the problem
of a contradiction. מידות Midos says the room was used for one
thing, תמיד Tamid for another, and it says it's because the author
of מידות Midos is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov.
Wasn't that fun? Okay.